# **UMESHA SANDALU**

## Software Engineer/Full Stack Developer

 @ sandykiara1995@gmail.com
https://github.com/sandalu95

umesha.vercel.appmedium.com/@sandalukalpanee

# **Professional Summary**

Aspiring IT professional with nearly 3 years of work experience in developing software solutions and enhancing system reliability. Skilled in multiple programming languages, such as Python, Java, JavaScript, and TypeScript, with extensive experience in technologies like React, Next.js, Node.js, and Spring Boot. Currently in the final semester of my Master's program with a 3.8 GPA and preparing for the AWS Cloud Practitioner certification exams. My skills in full stack development, system troubleshooting, and quality assurance can significantly contribute to your company's technological advancements and project success.

#### **Education**

### Master of Information Technology

**RMIT University** 

# Feb 2023 - Nov 2024

Melbourne, Australia

- Specialising in Cloud Computing and Big Data Management
- Current GPA of 3.80 out of 4.00.

## B.Sc. (Hons.) in Management and Information Technology

University of Kelaniya

**=** Feb 2016 - March 2020

Kelaniya, Sri Lanka

- Specialised in Information Technology
- Attained a GPA of 3.84 out of 4.00, obtaining a First Class.

# **Experience**

#### Software Engineer

WSO<sub>2</sub>

**m** Mar 2021 - Jan 2023

Oclombo, Sri Lanka

- Implemented the Choreo's marketplace feature with a team of developers, introducing a novel concept where organisations can host their APIs, event streams, and data sources.
- Designed and integrated user interfaces for Choreo Console's Mediation Ballerina service, facilitating seamless mediation customisation for API proxies.
- Contributed to the development of the low-code editor in Choreo, refining the statement editor panel and introducing components to enhance the overall user experience.
- Enhanced the code quality of Choreo by authoring comprehensive unit, integration and end-to-end tests using the React Testing Library and Cypress.
- Played a crucial role in handling production environment incidents during incident handling rotations, showcasing strong troubleshooting skills in resolving issues promptly.

#### Software Engineer

Cambio

**Mar 2020 - Mar 2021** 

Oclombo, Sri Lanka

- Played a pivotal role in the comprehensive development of both client and server modules for Cosmic Application.
- Specialised in troubleshooting and updating legacy software, making necessary modifications to fix bugs and ensure compatibility with new hardware.
- Elevated the software quality by writing robust unit tests and integration tests, contributing to the reliability and maintainability of the system.
- Actively participated in code validation tasks, identifying and resolving SonarQube issues to enhance code quality.
- Optimised the legacy codebase of Cosmic, resulting in a 9.7% reduction in processing time.

### Trainee Software Engineer (SE Intern)

WSO2

- **s** Sep 2018 Feb 2019
- Oclombo, Sri Lanka
- Collaborated with the API Manager team as a full-stack engineer, gaining hands-on experience with both front-end and back-end technologies.
- Developed the APIM Analytics dashboard, delivering a comprehensive individual project that enhanced data visibility and analytics capabilities for API management.
- Modified the API Manager Analytics database using Siddhi-streaming SQL, resulting in improved data querying performance and accuracy.

# **Projects**

- Soil Organic Food Retail Application (Online shopping cart application for SOIL Organic food retailer) Technologies - React, Node.js, Express, REST, GraphQL, MySQL
- School Management System (Web-based school management system for MR/Pitabeddara Secondary School) Technologies – Angular, Node.js, MongoDB, REST
- Woofy (Social networking platform to connect pet owners with pet service providers and associations)
   Technologies HTML, CSS, JS, PHP, Ionic, MongoDB, Firebase

# **Skills**

- Programming languages Python, Java, JavaScript, TypeScript, Ballerina and Bash
- Frameworks and tools React, Next.js, Angular, Node.js, Express, Git, Agile, and Testing (TestNG, Cypress)
- Databases MySQL, MongoDB, MSSQL, and Sqlite
- Cloud computing and DevOps tools AWS, Docker, and Kubernetes
- API Protocols REST and GraphQL
- UI/UX design tools Figma, Adobe XD, Adobe Photoshop, and Adobe Illustrator

# **Achievements**

- Placements on Dean's List in all four academic years of B.Sc.
- Member (2016-2020) in the University Karate team, winning national and inter-university medals.
- Business Development Director (2019) of LED club at the University of Kelaniya.
- Lead the Marketing and Communication function of AIESEC as the vice president (2018) at the University.
- Awarded as the Winner team of the Inventio 2017 competition organised by the University of Kelaniya.
- Became the 1st Runner Up team in CodeSprint 4.0 hackathon organised by IIT Sri Lanka.
- Semi-finalist of Biz Minds business planning competition organised by the young entrepreneurs' association of the University of Kelaniya.
- Held various leadership positions in the secondary school as a junior prefect and senior prefect.

# **Volunteering**

- Peer mentor (2023 2024) at RMIT University
- Volunteer (2024) at RUSU, RMIT University

## **Publications**

• "Sinhala language based social media posts analysis for the detection of suicidal risk." published in 2020 International Research Symposium on Pure and Applied Sciences